דף Daf is ע' Ayin but we are on ו' עמוד ב'
Vav Amud Bet and we're dealing with the new משנה Mishnah that
spoke about all of the invalid people or if you did it
with the left hand or not standing on the ground it's invalid
and then the statement of
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer ben... excuse me בן בתירא Ben Batera who
said that if you did it with the left hand put it
back in the כלי kli and do it again. So now we're
going to pick up with that in the גמרא. Gemara. So we
are on ו' עמוד ב' Vav Amud Bet
and the גמרא Gemara where it starts with אמר רב. Amar Rav.
It's about ten lines first word of the line ten lines from
the top or maybe
twelve אמר רב. Amar Rav. אמר רב זר שקמץ יחזיר. Amar Rav
Zar shekimet yachzir. So he takes the statement of the משנה Mishnah
with the left hand and he extends it even to a non-כהן.
Kohen. If a non-כהן Kohen does the קמיצה kmitzah just put it
back and do it again. So the גמרא Gemara says what do
you mean והנן פסול תנן? vanan pasul tnan? So first we're assuming
he's not anyway going like בן בתירא. Ben Batera. I mean on
the one hand it's an expansion of בן בתירא Ben Batera but
on the other hand it's going like בן בתירא. Ben Batera. So
the גמרא Gemara says the משנה Mishnah says everything except בן בתירא
Ben Batera that it's not good there's no way to fix it.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי פסול פסול עד שיחזיר? mai pasul
pasul ad sheyachzir? Talk about rewrites. The גמרא Gemara says what does
the משנה Mishnah mean when it says it's an invalid person does
it it's invalid? It's פסול pasul until you correct it but if
you correct it and put it back you can do it again.
You can have a you can have a do-over right
like it's a net but you know it's a net on the
serve. So anyway והא vaha so the גמרא Gemara says פסול עד
שיחזיר. pasul ad sheyachzir. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי היינו
בן בתירא. ee hachi haynu Ben Batera. So then it's בן בתירא
Ben Batera that's exactly what בן בתירא Ben Batera says is that
you can do a do-over.
Well maybe you can always be במצר b'metzar narrowly in your
say חכמים Chachamim are more מיקל meikel than בן בתירא Ben Batera
that you can't be.
אי הכי Ee hachi בן בתירא Ben Batera just saying you can
only you can do it over then he's saying then he's saying
בן בתירא Ben Batera would maybe say one more case even too.
Yeah but that would be expanding בן בתירא Ben Batera right now
we're trying to claim he's the רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay
so אי הכי היינו בן בתירא. ee hachi haynu Ben Batera. So
that's בן בתירא Ben Batera if he says that you can do
a do-over. So the גמרא Gemara tries to say that maybe the
רבנן Rabbis would agree to בן בתירא Ben Batera in a large
number of cases.
אי דאיתא לקומץ בעיניה לא פליגי רבנן עליה דבן בתירא. Ee de'itay
lekomet be'einay lo pligi Rabbanan alei deBen Batera. If you have the
same קומץ komet and you can really reverse the entire process start
it again from the beginning then the רבנן Rabbis would agree to
בן בתירא. Ben Batera. Everybody agrees you can do a do-over. לא
פליגי רבנן עליה דבן בתירא. Lo pligi Rabbanan alei deBen Batera. בכי
פליגי be'ki pligi when do they argue? דחסר קומץ dechasar komet that
you actually now don't have the original קומץ. komet. And the
question is can you refill the מנחה minchah from the lacking קומץ
komet with new grain? Because obviously that's a lot harder to view
that as a do-over than when you just you know quickly put
the stuff back. It's like on שבת Shabbos you know you walk
into a room right you walk into a room and you're not
thinking and accidentally turn on the light and say oh whoops and
you turn it back off right which makes it worse. But if
you do the same action in reverse you can understand not by
שבת Shabbos you can understand how we can think of that as
a do-over. If you have to get some more grain from your
house so that's maybe where the רבנן Rabbanan and בן בתירא Ben
Batera argue.
No but they're saying let's say a little bit like you know
it's walking through a house like some of it fell.
No but you'll see it's not. Okay so גמרא Gemara says אי
דאיתא לקומץ בעיניה ee de'itay lekomet be'einay
if the קומץ komet is still around לא פליגי רבנן עליה דבן
בתירא. lo pligi Rabbanan alei deBen Batera. They don't argue on him.
כי פליגי Ki pligi when do they argue? דחסר קומץ dechasar komet
that it's lacking. So maybe it's like Michael's case it's not all
there but I think this simply just means you don't have the
קומץ komet anymore.
רבנן סברי לא יביא מתוך ביתו וימלאנו. Rabbanan savri lo yavi mitoch
beito vayamleinu. You cannot now start again by bringing more flour and
oil from your house. בן בתירא סבר יביא מתוך ביתו וימלאנו. Ben
Batera savar yavi mitoch beito vayamleinu. Yep you can refill it from
your home. So that's a radical rewrite of the משנה Mishnah that
the whole debate is when you have to refill it from the
home. And the גמרא Gemara does not like it.
The גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ee hachi I'm sorry בן בתירא
אומר Ben Batera omer what do you do with the statement in
the משנה Mishnah where
בן בתירא Ben Batera says יחזיר ויחזור ויקמוץ בימינו? yachzir veyachzor veyikmot
biymino? בן בתירא Ben Batera
so it shouldn't have said that it should have said if we're
talking about refilling it from the home בן בתירא אומר יחזיר ויביא
מתוך ביתו Ben Batera omer yachzir veyavi mitoch beito reverse yourself go
back and bring more flour from your home וימלאנו ויחזור ויקמוץ בימינו
מיבעי ליה. vayamleinu veyachzor veyikmot biymino mibayei leh. He should have said
the simple the language is clear he means put the original קומץ
komet back. So give me a break they're not arguing about when
you have to get it from the home. בן בתירא Ben Batera
is talking when you're returning the original קומץ komet and even there
the רבנן Rabbis say it's no good. So we're back to the
question what did רב Rav mean to say that a זר zar
is good if he if he will be good if you just
redo it. So the גמרא Gemara says okay so
כי קאמר רב לבן בתירא. ki ka'amar Rav leBen Batera. All right
you're right. When רב Rav said a זר zar could redo it
he wasn't talking about the רבנן. Rabbanan. רבנן Rabbanan clearly don't hold
of redoes. He's talking according to בן בתירא. Ben Batera. But I
know we'll have to wait until we get to it. Okay so
The Rabbis are clearly talking about are rejecting בן בתירא, Ben Batera,
who's talking about re-dos, but he talks about using your left hand,
and the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is that they only
argue with the left hand, and as we discussed yesterday, Rav is
saying it's not limited to the left hand. It would include any
פסול psul according to בן בתירא, Ben Batera, you can do a
re-do. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
כי קאמר רב לבן בתירא. Ki ka’amar Rav Leven Batera. So פשיטא,
peshita, that's obvious. מהו דתימא, Mah d'teima, I might have thought, עד
כאן לא מכשר בן בתירא אלא בשמאל. ad kan lo machshir Ben
Batera ela b'smol.
So notice the גמרא Gemara thinks it's obvious right after they just
argued
that they argue even with other cases. No, I might have thought
עד כאן לא מכשר בן בתירא אלא בשמאל, ad kan lo machshir
Ben Batera ela b'smol, maybe בן בתירא Ben Batera is only allowing
a re-do with the left hand. אבל בשאר פסולים לא, Aval b'sha'ar
psulim lo, maybe not other invalidities. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan.
We're right before the line that begins with the ד dalet in
brackets, which is right above the line that begins with the ה
heh in a half bracket. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, well,
it's very easy to spot, it's about a third of the way
down. מאי שנא שמאל, Mai shna smol, how is your left hand
different? Meaning, why would I have thought, why is there a חידוש
chiddush in Rav's statement? It's a חידוש chiddush if I would have
had a reason to think that it would be somehow left hand
would be less of a problem than others, and maybe בן בתירא
Ben Batera only meant it by the left hand. Now again, textually,
from the language of the משנה, Mishnah, it seems like they're only
talking about left hand. But the גמרא Gemara still thinks like if
there's no good logic to explain why left hand would be different,
then I wouldn't I would have just assumed it was an example
and it did not mean specifically left hand. So why would I
have thought that left hand would have made a difference?
So מאי שנא שמאל, mai shna smol, דאשכחן להכשרה ביום כיפורים שמאל.
dashkechan lehachshara b'Yom Kippurim smol. Left hand is not always פסול. psul.
On יום כיפורים, Yom Kippurim, right, a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol uses
his left hand. He takes the when he brings in the incense
into the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, he takes in the fire pan
in his right, cause it's heavy, it has coals, and he takes
in the pan that has the incense in it in his left
hand. So there's a time we do use left hand, so it's
not absolutely invalid. Okay, so therefore, זר נמי, zar nami, so the
גמרא Gemara says, well, there are times where a non-כהן Kohen is
good. How is that? אשכחן להכשרה בשחיטה. ashkechan lehachshara b'shechitah. Every time
שחיטה shechitah can always be with a non-כהן. Kohen. So you see,
sometimes we allow a זר. zar. So now of course the גמרא
Gemara responds, שחיטה לאו עבודה היא. shechitah lav avodah hi. Right? No,
that's not an exception. It's not sometimes allowing a זר zar to
do an עבודה, avodah, it's because שחיטה shechitah isn't an עבודה. avodah.
We've discussed this before. How do we know שחיטה shechitah isn't an
עבודה? avodah? So רש"י Rashi very often, wisely, not here, says oh
because a זר zar can do it. But תוספות Tosafot says, no,
that would make this גמרא Gemara circular. Right? So you have to
be some other evidence that it's not an עבודה. avodah. So תוספות
Tosafot gives two answers. One is because we know from other places
you don't have to be standing in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
you can be standing in the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim when doing
the שחיטה, shechitah, and anything that's an עבודה avodah requires standing in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And the other answer as I've told
you before is because שחיטה shechitah is not uniquely, a distinctively for
the מקדש. Mikdash. You do שחיטה shechitah for all animals when you
want to then use eat the meat and so on, and therefore
even when it occurs in the מקדש, Mikdash, we're going to assume
that it's serving its generic purpose and not a specific מקדש Mikdash
purpose. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says since it's not an עבודה,
avodah, the fact that a non-כהן Kohen can do it does never
mean that we ever allow a non-כהן Kohen to do an עבודה.
avodah. All right, so let's see now where it goes on. So
you can just push that up a tiny bit more to the
center. Thank you.
Very well.
No, just a little center more.
Yeah. Want it move closer to you? Just horizontally more. That's it.
All right. Now, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says שחיטה לאו עבודה
היא. shechitah lav avodah hi. So the גמרא Gemara says ולא, v'lo,
is it not?
והאמר רבי
זירא
אמר רב,
V'ha'amar Rabbi
Zeira
amar Rav, didn't רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira say in the name of
רב, Rav, שחיטת פרה בזר פסולה? shechitat parah b'zar psulah? When you
slaughter the פרה, parah, when it says פרה parah without qualification, it
means פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
Every פרה אדומה, parah adumah, you can just as
well that's what it's going to say. Okay, Michael, I told you,
you can write the גמרא. Gemara. שחיטת פרה בזר פסולה. Shechitat parah
b'zar psulah. So if a non-כהן Kohen slaughters the פרה אדומה, parah
adumah, and this is outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it's invalid.
ואמר רב עלה, V'amar Rav alah, and רב Rav explained this, אלעזר
וחוקה כתיב בה, Elazar v'chukah ktiv bah,
because the תורה Torah says אלעזר Elazar and חוקה. chukah. It says,
you know, אלעזר הכהן, Elazar HaKohen, and it speaks about that this
is a חוק. chok. So חוק chok means exactly like this, so
not exactly אלעזר, Elazar, but anything that אלעזר Elazar symbolizes, which means
a כהן, Kohen, so not a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So you
see that you need a you need that. So the גמרא Gemara
says as Michael was saying more or less, שאני פרה דקדשי בדק
הבית היא. shani parah d'kadshai bedek habayit hi. Oh, פרה אדומה parah
adumah is not a real קרבן. korban. Slaughtered out of the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So its קדושה kedushah is בדק הבית. bedek habayit.
Now again, בדק הבית bedek habayit is a little imprecise because it's
בדק הבית bedek habayit is normally for things that are to fix
the מקדש, Mikdash,
you know, and but what the גמרא Gemara is trying to encapsulate
here is that it is not being its קדוש kadosh but not
being brought as a קרבן korban because it's being brought outside. So
normally the concept we have for קדושה kedushah that's not a קרבן,
korban, there's קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbe'ach and קדושת בדק הבית. kedushat bedek
habayit. So though קדושת בדק הבית kedushat bedek habayit normally means things
like כלי שרת klei sharet and building materials and all these things,
but it really now means anything that's not קדושת מזבח. kedushat mizbe'ach.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says Well, that's not such a bad
answer. Can we say קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
Well, that's my... oh, there you go. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, if it's not a קרבן korban and you need a
כהן, kohen, right? So
the גמרא Gemara says ולאו קל וחומר הוא, velav kal vachomer hu,
isn't it a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? קדשי בדק הבית בעו כהונה.
kodshei bedek habayit ba'u kehuna. If something that is not even strictly
a קרבן korban needs a כהן, kohen, קדשי מזבח לא בעו כהונה,
kodshei mizbayach lo ba'u kehuna, shouldn't a קרבן korban need a כהן?
kohen? And if it doesn't, it means that in principle it does,
but it's an exception, rather than saying that in principle it doesn't.
So then we can see that sometimes we allow a זר zar
to do something that really a כהן kohen should be doing. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב
ששת בריה דרב אידי, Amar Rav Sheshet breih deRav Idi, no. מידי
דהוה אמראות נגעים, Midi dehavei amara'ot nega'im, there are things that require
כהנים kohanim that are not about עבודות avodot in the מקדש, Mikdash,
like looking at a spot of צרעת tzara'at and declaring it טמא,
tamei, which can only be by a כהן. kohen. The גמרא Gemara
sometimes talks about let's say the כהן kohen doesn't know the laws
of צרעת, tzara'at, so he takes a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham with
him. The תלמיד חכם talmid chacham looks at it and tells him
whether it's טמא tamei or טהור, tahor, but the כהן kohen has
to utter the words טמא tamei or טהור, tahor, do that ritual
act to make it טמא tamei or טהור. tahor. Okay, so that
requires a כהן kohen and has nothing to do with קרבנות. korbanot.
דלאו עבודה נינהו, delav avoda ninhu, it's not an עבודה, avoda, ובעו
כהונה, uba'u kehuna, and it requires a כהן. kohen. So the גמרא
Gemara says the fact that a פרה אדומה para aduma requires a
כהן kohen does not prove for שחיטה shechita that שחיטה shechita in
principle requires a כהן. kohen. שחיטת קרבנות shechitat korbanot could in principle
not require a כהן, kohen, and if you think about it, I
mean if it would then לכתחילה lechatchila we would say maybe don't
use a non-כהן kohen and when the גמרא Gemara describes, for example,
קרבן פסח, korban pesach, it describes it that everybody is שוחט-ing shochet
their own קרבן. korban.
So anyway, it is not true. In principle, it does not require
a כהן, kohen, it is not an עבודה avoda and it can
be done with a זר zar and it's not an exception. פרה
אדומה Para aduma is its own story. And therefore the question is,
there would have been a very good הוה אמינא, hava amina, now
we understand, to say left hand would not be as bad as
other things and to be a redo, because you have left that's
allowed on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, other things you don't have that
they're ever allowed. Okay, so that explains why רב Rav had to
then expand it. Doesn't know how רב Rav knew to expand it,
but it's why he had to say that it's not limited to
left.
So the question is, you know, if it really is in everything,
then why didn't רב Rav just pick a different example?
Well, okay, so let's... I understand. It's like a double question. First,
we have to say why רב Rav needed to say it, then
we have to say what entitles רב Rav to say it. First,
we're working on why did רב Rav need to say it. Now
I do want to, by the way, point out an interesting point
here, that notice this original statement about that פרה אדומה para aduma
needs a כהן kohen was אמר רב זירא אמר רב, amar Rav
Zeira amar Rav, שחיטת פרה בזר פסולה, shechitat para bezar psula, and
then it says ואמר רב עלה. ve'amar Rav alah. So it's like,
so רב זירא Rav Zeira said in the name of רב Rav
a statement and then רב Rav commented on his own statement that
רב זירא Rav Zeira was repeating. So it's a little bit funny,
you know, what's going on there. But again, you know, it's like,
as I've explained before, the normal explanation of what does אמר רב
זירא אמר רב—by amar Rav Zeira amar Rav the time the גמרא
Gemara is recording it, there were ten people between רב זירא Rav
Zeira being written down in the גמרא. Gemara. So אמר רב זירא
אמר רב amar Rav Zeira amar Rav means that the first time
it was officially published, you know, which was sort of orally published,
told around but declared as a statement of רב, Rav, was through
the mouth of רב זירא. Rav Zeira. So you could have an
understanding where רב זירא Rav Zeira is going around teaching everybody this
teaching in the name of רב, Rav, publishing it, which is why
it gets remembered as אמר רב זירא אמר רב amar Rav Zeira
amar Rav even ten generations later, but then people start asking רב
Rav why is this? So then רב Rav has to comment on
his earlier statement. But it is interesting to see רב Rav commenting
on a statement that was said by רב זירא. Rav Zeira.
Okay, but what if somebody else said it in the name of
רב, Rav, but we don't have the name of the...
oh, you mean the second part, ואמר רב עלה. ve'amar Rav alah.
Could be, but right.
Okay, so now we understand why I would have said maybe only
left, but the גמרא Gemara is not done. The גמרא Gemara says
like
this: ונילף מבמה, venelef mibama, no, maybe זר zar also we allow
a זר zar sometimes. When do we sometimes allow a זר? zar?
In a במה. bama. Okay, so can't get rid of במות. bamot.
So the גמרא Gemara says, just like, you know, just like the
נביאים אחרונים, nevi'im acharonim, they couldn't get rid of the במות. bamot.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says...
or even some of... or even right, even the נביאים ראשונים—anyway, nevi'im
rishonim so the גמרא Gemara says ונילף מבמה, venelef mibama, וכי תימא
vechi teima מבמה לא ילפינן, mibama lo yalfinan, no, you can't learn
from במה, bama, that's an entire exception, that's, you know, nothing is
relevant from that world. No, והתניא, vehatanya, I'll show you where we
do learn from במה. bama. מניין ליוצא שאם עלה לא ירד? minayin
leyotzei she-im ala lo yered? How do I know that if something
went out of the מקדש Mikdash environs and then was put on
the מזבח, mizbayach, like the meat went out of the מקדש Mikdash
and then was put back on the מזבח mizbayach of an עולה,
olah, that you don't need to take it back down, that it's
allowed to stay on the מזבח? mizbayach? Right, there's the principle of
מזבח מקדש. mizbayach mekadesh. שהרי יוצא כשר בבמה, sheharei yotzei kasher bebama,
because it's not a total פסול psul going out, because by a
במה bama you didn't have a פסול psul of יוצא yotzei because
of course you could have a במה bama anywhere. Okay, so you
see we learn from what happened by a במה bama to say
that certain invalidities are not so bad. So here too, let's learn
that זר zar is not so bad because you have it in
a במה. bama.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, that's we're not really learning from
a במה bama there. תנא זאת תורת העולה סמיך ליה. tana zot
torat ha'olah samich leih. The תנא tana is relying... relying on the
פסוק pasuk of זאת תורת העולה. Zot Torat Ha'olah. תורה אחת לכל
העולים Torah achat l'chol ha'olim from the פסוק pasuk of זאת תורת
העולה Zot Torat Ha'olah we learn pretty much anything that goes on
the מזבח mizbeach gets to stay on, you don't take it off.
Now it's true there are a few exceptions, but it's not like
we really learn from a במה bamah that יוצא yotze is valid.
We really start with an assumption that everything that goes on the
מזבח mizbeach gets to stay there unless you can prove that it
deserves to be taken off. So therefore we're not really learning from
a במה. bamah. So we're back to score so we're back to
what we wanted to say. I would have had a reason to
think left was distinctive and רב Rav had to tell me not
only left. Okay, but now the גמרא Gemara is still not done.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא טעמא דאשמעינן רב. Ella taama d'ashmi'inan
Rav. So let's get this straight. So it's because רב Rav has
now told us that it's not only left. So you made a
good point, I could have thought only left, רב Rav now told
us not that way. הא לאו הכי, Ha lav hachi, if it
had not been for רב, Rav, הוה אמינא בשאר פסולים פסול בבן
בתירא, havei amina b'sha'ar psulim pasul b'Ben Betera, that בן בתירא Ben
Betera would have been invalidated other things. Yeah, I really would have
thought that. So the גמרא Gemara says והתניא, v'ha tanya, but we
have a ברייתא Baraita that's explicit.
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה ורבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומרים מחזיר היה בן
בתירא בכל הפסולים כולם. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon
omrim, machzir haya Ben Betera b'chol ha'psulim kulam. That they actually explicitly
state what רב Rav said. So we're saying רב Rav is anyway
redundant. Meaning you're right, now actually we've explained that yeah, I could
have explained the משנה Mishnah only about left. But why did רב
Rav have to be the one to tell me? There's a ברייתא
Baraita that tells me it's not only left.
And this ברייתא Baraita in מנחות? Menachot?
Yeah, it's related to yeah, I mean because you see
a משנה, Mishnah, so alright you have a ברייתא. Baraita.
I know, so the real way to explain it is is that
there's a debate about what בן בתירא Ben Betera said. רבי Rebbe
or you know whoever had that line in the משנה Mishnah that
was רבי Rebbe incorporated into the משנה Mishnah thought בן בתירא Ben
Betera said it only by left because as we just demonstrated there's
a reason to say left isn't as bad. These two תנאים Tannaim
thought בן בתירא Ben Betera said it like everybody like for all
invalidities. So the accurate you know the real read here is there's
a מחלוקת תנאים machloket Tannaim whether בן בתירא Ben Betera said it
only by left because we now said there's a good reason or
said it by all things. Okay, so that would actually be the
best answer. Maybe רב Rav understood it as a מחלוקת תנאים machloket
Tannaim and he was siding with the ברייתא Baraita that expanded בן
בתירא Ben Betera to all פסולים. psulim. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't
say it that way. The גמרא Gemara says if the ברייתא Baraita
makes it clear we should use the ברייתא Baraita to explain the
משנה. Mishnah. We should say it's clear בן בתירא Ben Betera said
it for all פסולים psulim and then who needs רב? Rav? Okay,
so that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
Maybe not everyone heard of this ברייתא? Baraita?
That is a very good answer. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says where are we? So the
גמרא Gemara says where are we? So okay where are we? והתניא
v'ha tanya etc. רב Rav etc. בכל הפסולים כולם b'chol ha'psulim kulam
ותניא v'tanya and we taught in a ברייתא Baraita וקמץ משם. v'kamatz
misham. It says that the כהן Kohen should take from there from
where the person brings the מנחה minchah he should take the קומץ.
kometz. So what does that mean? What do we learn out of
the word משם? misham? גזרת Gezeirat ממקום שרגלי הזר עומדות. mei'makom she'raglei
hazar omdot. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says it means where
the זר zar is standing. Which means that you know the first
eleven אמות amot after you get into the עזרה Azarah is where
ישראל Yisrael can stand. After that it's כהנים. Kohanim. So since it
says that the כהן Kohen takes from there, we learn out that
the כהן Kohen can take the קומץ kometz of מנחה minchah anywhere
in the עזרה. Azarah. Number one it doesn't only have to be
at the north of the מזבח. mizbeach. But number two it could
even be in the area that usually is where the ישראל Yisrael
is standing because it's from there, from wherever the ישראל Yisrael happens
to be. Anywhere in the עזרה. Azarah. Okay and because technically also
the ישראל Yisrael can be in the rest of the עזרה Azarah
although normally he's restrained to the first eleven אמות. amot. ממקום שרגלי
הזר עומדות. mimakom she'raglei hazar omdot. That's what he learns from the
word משם. misham. בן בתירא אומר, Ben Betera omer, no. מנין שאם
קמץ בשמאל שיחזיר ויחזור ויקמוץ בימין? Minayin she'im kamatz b'smol she'yachazir v'yachzor
v'yikmotz b'yamin? Here's how he learns it from a פסוק. pasuk. How
you know if you took with the שמאל smol you can put
it back and take it again with the right? תלמוד לומר וקמץ
משם, Talmud lomar v'kamatz misham, take your קמיצה kmitzah from there. ממקום
שקמץ כבר. mimakom she'kamatz kvar. Even from the place that it was
already taken from. So take your קמיצה kmitzah from there somehow means
from there from the place that you might have taken from before.
So that's the פסוק pasuk he learns it from. Okay now but
notice again he uses the example of שמאל. smol. But the גמרא's
Gemara going to say if you're basing yourself on a פסוק pasuk
why should you limit yourself to left? So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says וכיון דקרא סתם כתיב? v'keivan d'kra stam
ketiv? So since the פסוק pasuk is written סתם stam without making
distinctions, מה לי שמאל מה לי שאר פסולים? mah li smol mah
li sha'ar psulim? So obviously בן בתירא Ben Betera means not only
left but everything. Now again you could have said no, you know
just because again just because the פסוק pasuk says it's sometimes allowed
doesn't mean it's always allowed. Like if it became טמא tamei you
couldn't do it again. And maybe it's only things where there's a
logic to say you could do it again like the שמאל. smol.
But nevertheless although in the simple sense is what we've really got
here is a serious question whether בן בתירא Ben Betera said it
just by the שמאל smol or by other things and רב Rav
could be coming along to tell me we assume by everything. But
the גמרא Gemara even eliminates the question. It assumes since we have
these other sources we're going to assume that it's obvious בן בתירא
Ben Betera said it by not only left and therefore what's רב's
Rav חידוש? chidush? So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
אלא הא קמשמע לן רב. Ella ha kamashmalan Rav. This is what
רב Rav is teaching me. קמץ ואפילו קידש. Kamatz v'afillu kidesh. Okay
let's say.
So as you put it in the כלי שרת kli sharet already?
You get to put it back?
Exactly. Til when do you have a do-over? Like in chess, right?
You can do-over unless you lose your hand from, you know, from
the piece. Okay, so when is your time to have your do-over?
When is it like you removed your hand from? So if you
took it out, then you can put it back. But if you
take it out from this and you put it into the כלי
שרת kli sharet that the קומץ kometz goes into, that's maybe like
you took your hand off the piece. You can't do it again.
You've already established that it's in stage two and you can't do
a re-do of stage one. Okay, and that would have been a
reasonable assumption. But then if רב Rav goes further and after we
had all this evidence that בן בתירא Ben Beteira says it by
other things, רב Rav repeats it can even be by a non-כהן.
kohen. We understand that to mean even in a more extreme case,
even in a case where you already put it into the כלי
שרת. kli sharet. Okay, so let's read that.
So it
says קמץ ואפילו
קידש.
kamatz
va'afilu kidesh.
What do you do? You put that piece back or just go
and bring flour from your house?
No, no, no, you take that piece back. You still have to
reverse, but you can reverse even after.
Okay, so when is it, when does it become too late?
That is a good question. I mean it would be, obviously if
you've המקטיר, himktir, it's too late. But once you started doing הולכה,
holacha, according to רב, Rav, that's an interesting question. But on the
other hand הולכה holacha isn't always, isn't seemed as necessary, so it
doesn't necessarily describe another stage. I don't know, that's a good question.
So maybe not until it's like really gone.
Right, I don't know. Okay, so let's take a look. אלא הא
קמשמע לן
קמץ ואפילו קידש. ela ha kamashma lan kamatz va'afilu kidesh. ולאפוקי מהני
תנאי ulafokei mehanei tanna'ei and to exclude the opinion of the following
תנאים. Tanna'im. דתניא detanya we learn in a ברייתא, Baraisa, רבי יוסי
בן יוסי בן יאסיאן, Rabbi Yossi ben Yossi ben Yassian, very interesting
family name, יוסי בן יוסי בן יאסיאן. Yossi ben Yossi ben Yassian.
This was before רבי יהודה חסיד Rabbi Yehuda Chasid who said you
can't, you know, name a child after the father. ורבי יהודה הנחתום
אמרו, veRabbi Yehuda HaNachtom amru, and רבי יהודה הנחתום Rabbi Yehuda HaNachtom
said,
במה דברים אמורים שקמץ ולא קידש. bamei devarim amurim shekamatz velo kidesh.
When did בן בתירא Ben Beteira say you could do a do-over?
If you did the קמיצה kemitza without putting it into the next
כלי שרת. kli sharet. אבל
קידש, קידש פסל. aval kidesh, kidesh pasal. Then you've invalidated it. ואיכא
דאמרי ve'ika de'amri and there are those that say, קמץ אין, קידש
לא. kamatz in, kidesh lo. No, that exactly what רב Rav was
saying, that if the זר zar does the קמיצה, kemitza, you can
do a do-over. His emphasis was not to take it further, but
to underscore the word קמיצה. kemitza. As long as all you've done
is the קמיצה, kemitza, then you can do a do-over. But once
you put it in the next כלי, kli, it's you cannot. כמאן?
keman? And then רב Rav would be going like whom? כהני תנאי.
kehanei tanna'ei. Then he would not be rejecting those תנאים, Tanna'im, he
would be agreeing with them. ולאפוקי מתנא קמא, ulafokei miTanna Kama, and
to reject the opinion of the anonymous תנא Tanna that these תנאים
Tanna'im are arguing against, again, that would say that it's, that it
is even if you put it in a כלי. kli. So now
we have this question about when can you still do a do-over
to בן בתירא. Ben Beteira. Yes.
What constitutes the designation of some, of a particular measure of flour
as a מנחה? mincha?
So, when you take it from home and then you measure it
with a, actually, with measuring כלים keilim from the מקדש. Mikdash. And
then you put it in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So when
you put it in the כלי שרת, kli sharet, that defines that
as the מנחה. mincha.
And then putting it in the next, next כלי שרת.
kli sharet. So now you've brought it in, you have it in
this כלי שרת kli sharet and you bring it to the כהן,
kohen, and now he takes it from here and he's going to
put it in the next כלי שרת. kli sharet.
It's already a מנחה, mincha, but maybe going into the next כלי
שרת kli sharet already sort of says, now this act is done,
like you can't, you know, no do-overs.
Okay. הנחתום, HaNachtom, רבי יהודה הנחתום. Rabbi Yehuda HaNachtom.
The baker?
Oh, the baker.
Yeah, he was a baker.
Flour.
Oh, I see. I was wondering what you meant as that, how
he should know. Okay. Okay, that's an interesting point.
Was he around during that time?
I mean no, I don't, not necessarily.
No, he's, just because
he's a baker.
He was interested. It was an area of specialty of his. Okay,
anyway. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, מתקיף לה רב נחמן.
matkif lah Rav Nachman. So now, the last of the narrow lines,
so רב נחמן Rav Nachman asked on this,
מאי קסברי הני תנאי? mai kasvari hanei tanna'ei? What are these תנאים
Tanna'im holding? Meaning what is the significance of why the second כלי
שרת kli sharet means no do-overs? אי
קמיצה פסולה עבודה היא, i kemitza pesula avodah hi, if from the
moment they do the קמיצה kemitza that's an עבודה, avodah, but the
person being an עבודה פסולה, avodah pesula, so it already labels it
as פסול. pasul. So then אף על גב דלא עבדיה למתן כלי,
af al gav dela avdieh lamatten kli, even if you haven't yet
put it into the second vessel of the קמיצה. kemitza. אי קמיצה
פסולה לאו עבודה היא, i kemitza pesula lav avodah hi, if because
it's done by a פסול pasul person, normally of course קמיצה kemitza
is an עבודה. avodah. But if it's done by a פסול pasul
person, right? This is part of the logic of why you could
have a do-over, because you could say, since the person was invalid,
it's like nothing happened, right? You know, it's always the question, did
it happen in an invalid way and then it gets labeled and
thrown out, or did it like it wasn't even happening? So if
I hold that it wasn't, it's like it didn't even happen, כי
עבדיה למתן כלי מאי הוי? ki avdieh lamatten kli mai havei? So
who cares if you put it in a vessel, right? It's like
nothing happened yet, so do a do-over. הדר אמר רב נחמן, hadar
amar Rav Nachman, let me split my vote.
לעולם עבודה
היא.
le'olam avodah hi. No, no, no, it is an invalid עבודה avodah
and that's why you can't do do-overs, but why then only after
it's into the vessel? דלא גמרה עבודתה עד דעבדיה למתן כלי. dela
gamrah avodatah ad de'avdieh lamatten kli. The עבודה avodah isn't done. You're
still in the middle of the עבודה avodah until you get to
the next stage. So it is an עבודה פסולה, avodah pesulah, but
while you're still in the עבודה, avodah, you can still correct it.
When you finish the עבודה avodah and now it's past history, it
can no longer be corrected. Makes a lot of sense. Okay, blazes
the question about what's the opinion of those that say even after
מתן כלי? matan kly? Maybe they might hold of the other position
the גמרא Gemara suggested, that it's not even considered an עבודה avodah
when done invalidly. And since it's not an עבודה, avodah, you can
always reverse it, which also goes to your question about maybe even
after הולכה holacha and so on. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אי הכי, ee hachy, if that's true, let's skip a line. לומר,
lehmar, אי הכי, ee hachy, if that's true, אפילו לא קידש, afillu
lo kadesh, and even if you didn't put it in the second
כלי, kli, I'm going to create a problem for you. Why? Top
of ז' עמוד א'. zayin amud aleph. וכי מהדר ליה לקומץ לדוכתיה,
vechi mahader leh lekoametz leduchteh, תקדש ולפסול. tikdosh velifsul. So okay, you
put it back in the original כלי שרת. kli shares. But let
the original כלי שרת kli shares be counted as your second כלי
שרת. kli shares. Okay, so you take it and you put it
back into the original כלי שרת. kli shares. So now that should
be the קדושה kedusha of the קומץ kometz and define it as
the process was done. Because nothing says it has to be a
different כלי שרת. kli shares. Alright, although תוספות Tosfos says well why
isn't there a חציצה chatzitzah problem? Because you've got all the other
grain in there, so you know, all the other flour. So says
מין במין לא, min bemin lo, you know, is לא חוצץ. lo
chotzetz. So nothing says that when you put the קמיצה kmitzah in
a כלי, kli, it has to be a different כלי. kli.
What? We saw the לבונה levonah in there.
You saw the לבונה levonah in there. But you don't put it
on the לבונה, levonah, let's say, okay. And anyway, now that you've
done the act of קמיצה, kmitzah, you can just burn everything on
the מזבח, mizbeach, right? Because you're burning, okay you don't get to
eat the קרבן, korban, but you're burning the קמיצה, kmitzah, you're burning
the לבונה. levonah. Mixing it with the לבונה levonah is only a
problem before the act of קמיצה kmitzah because then you're not taking
a full קמיצה. kmitzah. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what?
Put it back in the כלי. kli. You've already ended the act
now as well. So, אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, what?
Like when you put it in the כלי kli with things that
don't go on the מזבח? mizbeach?
Well, yeah, well, you
mean not תוספות's Tosfos's question about חציצה, chatzitzah, but a question about
like, I don't know, what would you say if I had this
big כלי kli that I was putting the מנחה minchah in and
there happened to have been, I don't know, some leftover whatever in
it, I left my cigarette butt in it or something, right? Would
you say that it's not a קדושת כלי kedushas kli if there's
not a חציצה chatzitzah problem?
Alright, so I don't know. So the גמרא Gemara thinks that it
would be okay, right? But I think what the real question is
is why don't we allow context to define what's going on here?
That what's going on is a do-over and not a continuing of
the process. So the גמרא Gemara sort of says that. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. So אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan,
זאת אומרת, zos omeres, this says, כלי שרת אין מקדש אלא מדעת.
kly shares ain mekadesh ella mida'as. A כלי שרת kli shares is
only effective if you intend it to be effective to define the
קדושה. kedusha. So by the way, one thing you have to learn
here and one of the interesting parts of מנחות Menachos that we
did not really get too much of in זבחים Zevachim is how
כלי שרת kly shares works. Because by קרבנות, korbanos, okay, you did
have a כלי שרת kli shares that you caught the blood. But
basically you were not, didn't have too many כלים keilim around. By
מנחות Menachos you have a lot of כלים keilim around. You know,
you bring it in a כלי, kli, the flour, you measure it,
you mix it, you do the קמיצה, kmitzah, you put it whatever.
So there's going to be a lot of discussion of how כלי
שרת kly shares operate. And one of the things you learn is
that קדושה kedusha is not all or nothing, it's not binary. That
this מנחה minchah could be קדוש kadosh as a מנחה, minchah, but
then the קמיצה kmitzah you put it in the next כלי kli
and that gets another level of קדושה. kedusha. And now it's designated
to be brought on the מזבח mizbeach and so on. So Rav
is saying here a general statement that כלי שרת kly shares don't
have their effect unless you intend for them to. So therefore, if
I just, let's say, you know, that's good and bad. Let's say
I didn't realize this was a כלי שרת kli shares and I
was just pouring my מנחה minchah into it. It would not have
the קדושה kedusha and I'd have to put it again into a
כלי שרת kli shares with the intent that this was to designate
it and to sanctify it and so on. If you say that...
So here, when he says that if you put it back in
the first one, you're not trying to designate it as the קומץ,
kometz, you're trying to do a do-over.
So if when you put it back in the first one you
said, "Oh, I don't have any כלי kli available, I'll put it
back in the first one and that'll be work for my קומץ,"
kometz, that would work. Okay, in theory it could work. But that's
not what you're doing here. You're doing a do-over. And the כלי
שרת kly shares does not work if you don't want them to
work. Yes.
To avoid this whole problem, then you know, even when you do
from the very beginning, even if it's a כהן פסול kohen pasul
and this
and this and that, then just...
You cannot retroactively remove your דעת. da'as.
No, just the best thing is to not have anything in mind
in the beginning at all when you're doing it and then just
do with the דעת da'as in the end. That way you won't
have any problems with doing it...
No, no, you want to retain the right to determine at the
end whether it worked or not.
That's my point.
Yeah, but you can't do that. Okay, at the moment you put
it in the כלי שרת kly shares you have to determine. If
it was לדעת leda'as it's קדוש, kadosh, if it's not לדעת leda'as
it's not קדוש. kadosh. Yeah, there's no stipulating. You're right, if we
sort of played these games, it will count בתנאי betnai that it's
done the right way, but the גמרא Gemara never, never goes that
far.
This is a reverse of
פיגולי. piguly.
And here you validate or you raise the קדושה kidusha. *kedushah*. Yeah,
that's a very good point, like the strength of כוונה *kavanah* that
things don't just happen because the rituals are done. There's this strength
of how you're intending it, and even by קדושה *kedushah* where you
might think, you know, the whole idea like מזבח מקדש mizbeiach mekadesh.
*mizbeach mekadesh*, you know, that there it almost does happen by itself.
You put it on the מזבח mizbeiach *mizbeach* and the connection to
the מזבח mizbeiach *mizbeach* means it gets to stay. Here we don't
say that by כלי שרת kli shareis *klei sharet*. Yeah, your thought,
that's an excellent point. Right, the centrality of thought, that's an excellent
point.
You know the סמיכה *smicha* for the animals, that's your, that's the
donor's...
Right, although even if you didn't do סמיכה *smicha*, it's still כשר
kasher. *kosher*. But here the thought is really critical according to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. It's a very good point.
Okay, I kind of lost track of what we were trying to
do here.
So what we were trying to do is say, Rav said you
can do a do-over, בן בתירא *Ben Betira* said you can do
a do-over even with your left hand. Rav's with your left hand.
Rav said it's not limited to left hand. We saw that there
were other ברייתות *braitas* that expanded בן בתירא *Ben Betira* that way
as well. Then he said, so what's Rav's חידוש chiddush? *chiddush*? So
using this question of what's Rav's חידוש chiddush *chiddush*, whether this is
or isn't Rav's חידוש chiddush *chiddush*, we introduced this question of when
can you do a do-how long into the process can you do
a do-over for בן בתירא *Ben Betira*? Only until the כלי kli.
*cli*-the second כלי kli *cli* or even after you put in the
second כלי kli *cli*. The גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s now working with this
idea that once you put in the second כלי kli *cli*, it's
too late, you're on to the next stage, and therefore you cannot
do a do-over. And then the question is, okay, but then even
when you do a do-over, that should count as the second stage
because it's now in a כלי שרת klei shareis *klei sharet*. Says
no, that doesn't count as the second stage, that's only מדעת *midaas*.
Okay, so now we have basically said that the according to the
opinion you can do a do-over, it's not limited to left, but
it does seem a strong emphasis that it would not apply once
it was in a כלי שרת kli shareis. *klei sharet*, and we've
now introduced a second כלי שרת kli shareis, *klei sharet* because then
it's at the next stage, and we've introduced this new idea of
כלי שרת kli shareis, אין מקדשין אלא מדעת *klei sharet ein mekadeshin
ela midaas*. And now what the גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s going to do,
what according to בן בתירא *Ben Betira*, we're not saying we're פוסקנינג
*paskening* בן בתירא *Ben Betira*, it's just a curious position and we're
exploring it. Now the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is going to shift its
emphasis to explore this question about כלי שרת kli shareis מקדשין אלא
אין כלי שרת kli shareis מקדשין אלא מדעת *klei sharet mekadeshin ela
ein klei sharet mekadeshin ela midaas*. So for now we're going to
bracket בן בתירא *Ben Betira* of do-overs and focus on כלי שרת
kli shareis. *klei sharet*. Gonna get back to it? Okay, we'll see.
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay, so
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says, הא מדעת מקדש mekadesh *ha midaas mekadesh*,
so are you saying that with intention they are מקדשין *mekadeshin*? Meaning,
and the point here being even something that's פסול posul *pasul*, like
this קמיצה kemitza שמאל *kmitza smol*, would you say that מדעת *midaas*
it is מקדש mekadesh *mekadesh*? והא בעא מיניה ריש לקיש Reish Lakish.
מרבי יוחנן *veha b'ai minei Reish Lakish meiRabbi Yochanan*, it's the same
רבי rebbi. יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* asks
רבי Rebbe. יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, כלי שרת kli shareis מה שיקדשו פסול
posul? לכתחילה *klei sharet ma sheyakdishu pasul l'chatchila*? Can we קרב *kareiv*,
if you, can you use a כלי שרת kli shareis, *klei sharet*
to take something פסול psul? *pasul* and make it valid to be
offered? Now that sounds pretty radical. I'll unpack that in a minute,
but let's see what he answers. ואמר ליה *va'amar lei*, אין מקדש
mekadesh *ein mekadesh*, no, even if you try it doesn't work. So
you see here that even מדעת *midaas* it doesn't work if it's
פסול posul *pasul*, and here it's also פסול pasul *pasul*. So the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says, אמר ליה amar lei *amar lei*, or אמר
*amar*, אין מקדש mekadesh לקרב אבל מקדש mekadesh לפסול *ein mekadesh l'kareiv
aval mekadesh l'pasel*. No, he said was a כלי שרת kli shareis,
*klei sharet* can't work to take something invalid and make it valid,
make you allowed to be מקריב makriv *makriv* it. But here it's
taking something invalid, קמיצה kemitza, שמאל *kmitza smol*, and saying you reached
the second stage and you can't do a do-over. So it can
have enough קדושה *kedushah* to just designate it at the second stage,
which is not enough קדושה *kedushah* to make it valid. Okay, so
that makes an enormous amount of sense. What doesn't make sense is
the הוה אמינא hava amina *hava amina* of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
*Reish Lakish*. Where does this crazy idea that you could actually be
מקריב לכתחילה *makriv l'chatchila* something that was פסול *pasul* because you put
it in a כלי שרת kli shareis *klei sharet*? So רש"י *Rashi*
actually interprets it literally. We literally think that maybe כלי שרת klei
shareis *klei sharet* has the power that if I intentionally catch it
with a דעת da'as. *daas* to be מקריב *makriv* it, you know,
put it in this כלי kli *kli*, that maybe I can, the
קדושה *kedushah* can make it fit
on the מזבח mizbeiach, *mizbeach*.
It's kind of like המזבח מקדש Mikdash. *hamizbeach mekadesh*, but it's even
more than המזבח מקדש *hamizbeach mekadesh*, it actually makes it effective as,
it removes the פסול *psul*. It's more like a ציץ מרצה *tzitz
meratzeh* or something.
So it can, so you can alleviate פיגול pigul *piggul* that way.
Right, well that's תוספות Tosafos *Tosfot*'s question. תוספות Tosafos *Tosfot*'s question is
that, oh my god, then why haven't we gotten rid of all
the פסולי זבחים *psulei zvachim*? You're always מקבל *mekabel* the דם dam.
בכלי *dam b'kli*, right, so how do we not get rid of
all of those פסולים *psulim*? Now, maybe it makes a difference if
the פסול *psul* is in the דם dam. *dam*, then maybe the
דם *dam* sitting in the כלי kli *kli* can remove it. פיגול
*piggul*, נותר *notar*, טמא *tamei*, where it's in the meat or it's
in the whole קרבן korban, *korban*, that was not connected to the
כלי kli. *kli*. But תוספות Tosafos *Tosfot* at least asks when we
deal with פסולי דם *psulei dam*, why don't we ever say that
the כלי kli, *kli* can't-you know, why was that never raised as
a question? Are מנחות menachos *menachot* and קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* different? Well,
that would be an interesting question. Right, whether although there is קדושת
כלי kli, *kedushat cli* by קרבנות *korbanot* because of the דם *dam*,
that somehow the דם *dam* is much more intrinsically the lifeforce of
the animal, and the whole role of כלי kli *kli*, even when
it exists by a בהמה *behemah* קרבן korban, *korban*, an animal קרבן
korban, *korban*, right, is somehow less significant in designating its identity and
its קדושה *kedushah* than by מנחות Menachos? *menachot*. That is definitely a
tantalizing possibility.
Right,
so that really is the question.
How do you go to this whole משנה Mishnah that says anybody,
a פסול person that does the, that does the עבודה, avoda, right,
it's פסול? Why don't we just say, well, just put it in
a כלי שרת kli shareis and then you could get rid of
that פסול? So that is definitely true. And that's really, you know,
תוספות'ס Tosafos's answer is we never really, but I do want to
say that, and that is something I want us to keep in
mind, that what Dov just raised is an important question. I said
before that we're going to do a lot about how כלי שרת
klei shares operate. It's also interesting to think about, you know, we
do have the one place, one or possibly two, one or two
places they operate by a קרבן, korban, by, you know, by an
animal. One is שחיטה shechita if it is כלי שרת. klei shares
The רמב"ם Rambam says it doesn't have to be. And the other
is קבלה kabala of the דם. But the question is, maybe they
have more of a role, not just more frequent, what they do
is more significant when it's in the מנחה mincha than when it's
in the דם. That is something to think about. But going back
to תוספות'ס Tosafos's point,
תוספות Tosafos says no, the only הוה אמינא hava amina, even for
ריש לקיש. Remember this is only a הוה אמינא, hava amina it's
rejected. But the only הוה אמינא even for ריש לקיש was sort
of like מזבח mizbeiach מקדש. What he did not mean was that
it would you could ממש mamash be מקריב it and יוצא yotzei
your קרבן, but if it's in the כלי שרת, klei shares maybe
it's like it's on the מזבח mizbeiach. already, and maybe now I
can put it on the מזבח mizbeiach. to let it burn. I
don't have to destroy it, get rid of it. Not I'm יוצא
yotzei my קרבן, but in terms of the physical object that's in
the כלי שרת, klei shares maybe being in the כלי שרת klei
shares is like being on the מזבח, mizbeiach? and now I can
move it to the מזבח mizbeiach, and let it burn on the
מזבח. Okay, so that's a reasonable question. Nobody's trying to מכשיר machshir
the קרבן, they're just trying to keep get this thing on the
מזבח. That's how the תוספות Tosafos understood the question. And again, the
answer is no. הגמרא The gemara says okay, no to do that,
but enough to say you reached the second stage and you can't
do a do-over. And now the גמרא'ס gemara's going to continue to
explore the, wait
so now we're not asking then according to שמעון בן בתירא Shimon
ben Beseira how can you do the do-over or?
No, we were just saying if, the question was, is that how
could you say that the כלי שרת klei sharet. is effective once
it's פסול if we know let's say that רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
said no to ריש לקיש which let's say means you can't put
it on the מזבח? So okay, you can't put it on the
מזבח, but it's effective enough to say you got to the second
stage and you can no longer do a do-over.
Then you can somehow still do a do-over with this
before you got to the second stage. Yeah, but this is the
second stage, in other words, you put it in the other one
and then according to that position, שמעון בן בתירא Shimon ben Beseira
you can still put it back.
No, we're not, right, there is the position that even after, but
we're dealing with the position that you can't put it back after
the כלי שרת. kli sharet Okay. So now the גמרא gemara moves
is going to focus on the כלי שרת klei sharet aspect. So
let's take a look. Okay, רב עמרם אמר Rav Amram amar כגון
שהחזירו לביסה גדושה. kegon shehechiziru levisa gedusha.
So the גמרא gemara says here's why, well we're going back to
the original question. Why when he put it back in the כלי
שרת, klei sharet in the original כלי שרת, klei sharet is that
not like he reached stage two? Okay, even though it was the
original, let the כלי שרת klei sharet define it, the original one,
as stage two. So until now we've been saying it doesn't work
without דעת. da'as. Now we're going to say maybe כלי שרת klei
sharet don't need דעת. da'at So then why is not putting it
back considered stage two? Because he didn't really put it back. Why
didn't he really put it back? Because the מנחה mincha was overflowing
the כלי. kli, And when you put it back, you actually put
it not in the כלי kli. but on the mound of the
מנחה mincha and if it's not in the כלי keli. itself, it's
not קדוש. kadosh. So that's why it didn't work. But the point
for us is also, according to this, a כלי שרת klei sharet.
is even שלא מדעת. shelo mida'as.
You don't need even overflowing because even if it's in in.
All right, that's what we're getting. So the גמרא gemara says ומקמץ
היכי קמץ? umikematz heichi kamatz? So how did you do the קמיצה
kemitza originally? That type of a מנחה mincha is not כשר. kasher.
It all has to be in the כלי keli for it to
be כשר. So the גמרא gemara says alright, הכא שהחזירו לביסה טפופה.
hacha shehechiziru levisa tefufa. He returned it to a כלי keli that's
what a ביסה bisa means, טפופה tefufa like flattened, meaning it only
reached the lip.
So a ביסה bisa is a
כלי keli and טפופה tefufa is like
like padded down. Okay, וכיון דקמץ ליה, vekeivan dekametz lei, once you
did the קמיצה, kemitza so עבד ליה גומא, avid lei guma, so,
okay, so טפופה, tefufa, I'm sorry. So that's the answer. So okay,
it's flat, but when I put the קמיצה kemitza back on the
flat part of the מנחה, mincha, I'm not putting it in the
כלי. keli The, right, the קמיצה kmitza. is over the edge of
the כלי, keli so it's not קדוש kadosh again. So the גמרא
gemara says one second, who says you put it down on the
flat part? Why don't you put it back into the hole that
you created? So the גמרא gemara says וכיון דקמץ ליה עביד ליה
גומא, vekeivan dekametz lei avid lei guma, when you did the קמיצה
kmitza. you made a hole, you know, an indentation, an indent, a
well, okay, right, not exactly a hole. Okay, כי מהדר ליה לגבי
דמנא קמהדר. ki mahadar lei legabei demana kamahadar.
So when you're putting it back, it's going back into that indent
and it's going back into the כלי, keli. so it should מקדש
it. So the גמרא gemara says מהדר ליה. mahadar lei. So the
גמרא Gemara says no. מכי מהדר ליה מנח ליה אדפנא דמנא. miki
mahadar lei manach lei adafna demana.
When you're putting it back, you're just putting it at the lip
of the כלי keli and then it slides in by itself. ומנח
ליה ונפל ממילא. umanach lei venafal mimeila. As you move the כלי,
keli it slowly evens out. That is not considered an act of
putting it back into the כלי. keli דנעשה כמי שהחזירו הקוף. dena'aseh
kemi shehechiziro hakof. It's like the monkey put it back. Okay. So
the idea of using this model of a monkey that might evoke
something for some people around here is something that comes up in
the גמרא Gemara as something
as like a metaphor for way something can be done without a
person doing it. And therefore we don't have to say and therefore
even though it got done, it's either not a problem let's say
for example the monkey did the קמיצה. kmitza Would you say oh
so it's פסול you can't do it again? Or would you say
no that's not a קמיצה פסולה, kmitza psula, it's not a קמיצה.
kemitza? So that way it's not a problem. It also could mean
that it's not good. Let's say the let's say the monkey put
the מנחה mincha into the second כלי. keli He's not מקדש it
because it was not done by the act of the כהן. cohen.
So if the כהן cohen so here we're saying a כלי keli
works שלא מדעת, shelo mida’as, but even though it works שלא מדעת,
shelo mida’as, it needs an act. It needs an act of the
כהן. cohen. Okay you don't have to be intending to be doing
the to be מקדש but the כהן cohen needs to do the
act of putting it back. So if the כהן's cohen act is
putting it not in the כלי keli? but like on the flour
and it's rise it's above and then and then it has falls
into the כלי keli there is no act of putting it back
and therefore it's no good. Okay so just to realize what we're
doing we're having a really of our first central discussion of how
כלי שרת klei sharet works. Number one does it require intent? Number
two even if it doesn't require intent minimally it requires a act,
a conscious act. And that's not what you have here.
Wait I'm so confused. So he's saying that the only way
so for him to do the do over correctly he has to
put it like back in the from the exact spot that he
took it off?
No he has to put it in the כלי kli it doesn't
have to be the back exact spot but it can't be it
can't be the walls of the כלי kli are מקדש what is
contained within them not what is overflowing above them. So he put
it overflowing and then it fell in but he did not actively
put it into the כלי.
kli You said a conscious act so I'm not sure if you
meant that but what if the person was sleepwalking?
Right so I so that would be like מתעסק. misasek. So I
don't so I mean we're not we in a way I think
that the גמרא Gemara. is alluding to that here because notice the
גמרא Gemara. says that when it says how it fell in it
says ומני ליה ונפיל ממילא. umani lei venafil mimeila. He moves the
כלי kli. and it falls on its own. So wait a minute
if his movement of the כלי kli is causing it to slip
he is moving it so that would be מתעסק misasek right? If
you're not so that is why I did say conscious act. All
right okay so the גמרא Gemara. says like this. אמר
ליה רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא. amar lei Rabbi Yirmiya le’Rabbi Zeira. So
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya said to רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. ולוקמה כגון
שהחזירה לכלי המונח על גבי קרקע. velokma kegon shehechezira likli hamunach agabi
karka. Here's another question: does the כלי שרת klei sharet. have to
be held by a person in order for it to for it
to function? Right normally we talk about you know the כהן cohen
is standing on the ground and he's connected to the ground and
somehow that creates this whole system of קדושה. What if the כלי
שרת klei sharet. is on the ground without a כהן? cohen? Does
it require human agency in the holding? We just said it required
human agency in the placing, does it require human agency in the
holding? Now you could see why say no because even if a
כהן cohen is holding it you know it's what the גמרא Gemara
calls in other places מעשה אצטבא. ma'aseh itztiba. He's serving like a
platform. You know even holding it isn't really doing an act. You
could be just a you know a shtender. So maybe it could
be right on the ground. Do you need do you need that
for כלי שרת kli sharet to operate? So let's take a look.
כגון שהחזירה לכלי המונח על גבי קרקע אלא שמע מינה kegon shehechezira
likli hamunach agabi karka ela shema mina since you did not bother
giving that answer that that would have been an example where the
where putting it back into the first כלי kli did not re-מקדש
it.
So since you did not give that answer שמע מינה קומצי מכלי
שעל גבי קרקע. shema mina komtzi mikli she’al gabi karka. You can
take the קמיצה kemitza even from the כלי kli that is on
the ground. It does not matter who is holding the כלי kli
or whether it's being held. So so then he said to him
either אמר ליה amar lei, or whatever he said כנגעת בבעיא דבעיא
לן. kanagat bevaya dibaya lan. You have you've touched on the question
that we were asking. We in the בית מדרש beis medrash were
asking exactly this question of do you need a כהן cohen to
hold the כלי? kli Does it matter who's holding whether the כלי
kli is being held? דרב אבימי תני מנחות בי רב חסדא. deRav
Avimi tani menachos bei Rav Chisda. רב אבימי Rav Avimi was learning
מנחות Menachos. in the ישיבה yeshiva of
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. ואבימי בי רב חסדא תני? veAvimi bei Rav
Chisda tani? Wait a minute did אבימי Avimi learn from רב חסדא?
Rav Chisda? We know that אבימי Avimi is רב חסדא's Rav Chisda
רבי. Rebbe. ואמר רב חסדא. ve’amar Rav Chisda.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda said in a totally different context כופי תבי
kufi tavi a lot of smacks כופי kufi is like a a
hit a smack איבעי מאבימי eba’i mei’Avimi I absorbed from אבימי Avimi
mean now again I hope it means it metaphorically but maybe not
they believed in corporal punishment in those days so אבימי Avimi really
like smacked me up אלא דהא שמעתא. ala deha shmaitsa.
Because אבימי Avimi we had a problem there were too many in
ערכין erchin which it talks about you know a בית דין's beis
din role in like seizing property it starts with קרבנות but it
goes to other things. So let's say you have orphans and they
owe money and בית דין beis din has to collect some of
their property. So בית דין beis din wants to make sure the
orphans get a good deal so they make announcements in all the
newspapers in all the public forums that this is for sale and
they have a and they have an auction so that they can
get the best deal for it. So one ברייתא brayisa says thirty
days and for for they make these announcements and one says sixty
days. So אבימי Avimi said here's the answer if you're making the
announcement every If you're making the announcement every day, then it's thirty
days. If you're only making the announcement on Mondays and Thursdays, which
are the market days, then it's sixty days. It's not the same
number of days, but it's over a longer period of time and
it's when it gets more publicity. So, so that's what אבימי Avimi
said. So רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, I'm sorry, not רב חסדא Rav
Chisda thought that was such a brilliant answer and he went around
praising אבימי Avimi and then it says that אבימי Avimi slapped him
up. Again, I don't know if it means that literally because he
said, you know, you shouldn't, like, don't go around singing my praises.
So that's like a whole interesting story there. So he says, I
got a lot of smacks from אבימי Avimi על דא שמעתא al
da hashmaita based on this teaching. בא לחלוט וצופין שלושים יום, ba
lachlot u'tzofin sheloshim yom,
if you're making the announcement continuously you do it for thirty days.
שני וחמישי, sheni v'chamishi, if you're making the announcements on Mondays and
Thursdays, then שישים יום, shishim yom, sixty days. So anyway, what do
you see? You see that אבימי Avimi was the רבי. Rebbe, So
what's אבימי Avimi going to רב חסדא's Rav Chisda house to learn
מנחות? Menachos. So the גמרא gemara, says אבימי מסכתא איתעקרא איתעקר ליה,
Avimi masechta it'akra it'aker lei, אבימי, Avimi,
the מסכת Masechet was uprooted from him, which means like maybe he
was getting old, losing his memory, okay? And he so he was
really having a hard time, you know, he didn't really remember מנחות.
And of course remember, in a time of an oral culture memory
was key because like nowadays we, you know, there's a lot, the
New York Times was just talking about this whole book by this
guy Foer, what was his first name? Joseph? Josh? Because you know
about, and I've definitely found this myself, the externalization of memory. The
more things are available on the internet, the less we remember anything.
You know, and I there are times, you know, גמרות Gemaros and
ראשונים Rishonim and things that I could have remembered once I started,
you know, trying to use the בר אילן Bar Ilan or whatever,
all of a sudden I started remembering them less because I didn't
force myself as much to remember them. So in a time when,
so nowadays, you know, the גמרא gemara can remember all the text
for me and I just have to remember, you know, my סברא
svara or whatever that I had as a גמרא.
Gemara You just remember where it was in the גמרא.
Gemara Where it was in the גמרא. Gemara Anyway, so when it
was all an oral culture,
everybody's basic thing you needed first of all was the text. So
if you were, even if you still had your, like, you know,
your
sharpness of your thought, if you did not have the text memorized
you had to go to somebody that had the text memorized. And
the ברייתא Baraita that says תני מנחות tani Menachos does not necessarily
mean the word תני tani means that he was learning the text
of מנחות. Okay? So that's what it's saying. He lost his memory
of this מסכת Masechet and he needed to relearn the text from
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda.
That happened to רב יוסף Rav Yosef too, no?
Yeah, but רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, it just he more generally just
forgot everything and he forgot even things that he had taught. Okay?
That, but that's not like remembering the, you know, the base text.
Forgetting the, this is just I think the base text he forgot.
Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מסכתא איתעקרא איתעקר ליה,
masechta it'akra it'aker lei, he lost that מסכת, Masechet, it was uprooted
from
him, ואתא קמיה דרב חסדא לאדכורי גמרא, v'ata kamei de'Rav Chisda l'idkurei
gemara, and he went to רב חסדא Rav Chisda to remember his
tradition. Notice again the key word, to remember, right? It's not like
רב חסדא Rav Chisda was necessarily the bigger תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham.
He was the רבי. Rebbe And with גמרא, Gemara גמרא Gemara here
means, you know, some more like the tradition that's handed down. So
he is trying to recover the text. All right?
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says ולישלח ליה וליתי, v'lishlach lei v'leiti,
we're still not done with this. If he was the רבי, why
not send a messenger to go get רב חסדא Rav Chisda לגביה
וליתי לגביה, legabei v'leiti legabei, and have רב חסדא Rav Chisda come
to him?
Come to him. סבר הכי מסתייעא מילתא טפי. savar hachi mistaya milta
tfei. No, I'll have more סיעתא דשמיא Siyata DiShmaya if I go
to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. That, so or maybe either this was
a belief, like, if I humble myself, you know, rather than be
arrogant, you know, that's putting, but it also could, you know, then
I'll get God will be with me more. But it also could
be practically, you know, that if you more position yourself as a
תלמיד, Talmid, you're more open to receive. If you're, you know, holding
on to your רבי status, you're not going to be as open
to receive.
He was very humble from the beginning of the story too
when he smacked him around. Oh, but because he didn't allow him
to go praising him, that's true. Right, he was humble, maybe a
little violent, but humble. Okay. So, so the גמרא says like this.
Okay. Good point. All right. פגע ביה רב נחמן. paga bei Rav
Nachman. So now we're finally back to our story. So אבימי Avimi
was learning in the house of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. פגע ביה
רב נחמן. paga bei Rav Nachman. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman bumped
into אבימי. Avimi. אמר ליה, amar lei, כיצד קומצין? keitzad komtzin? How
do you do קמיצה? kmitza So אמר ליה, amar lei, מכלי זה.
mikli zeh. Like this כלי right here that's on the ground. You
could take it from a vessel such as that. אמר ליה, amar
lei, וכי קומצין מכלי שעל גבי קרקע? vechi komtzin mikli she'al gabei
karka? What? Are you saying you can do קמיצה from a כלי
on the ground? So he said, no, no, no. אמר ליה, דמגבה
ליה כהן. d'magbah lei kohen. No, no, I didn't mean in the
position it's in. I meant if the כהן Kohen was holding it.
So תוספות of course says then what's the חידוש? So תוספות tries
to figure out what the חידוש might be. What was the question?
So תוספות says, well, maybe it was like a wood vessel. And
the חידוש was you could have a כלי שרת kli sharet out
of a wood vessel. I think פשט pshat is that he doesn't
remember this stuff yet, right? So he didn't actually, oh yeah, טאקע
takke I hadn't thought about that. Oh, I meant you were holding
it. Something like that. Okay, look how the story continues. כיצד מקדשין
את המנחות
*Keitzad mekadshtin es haminchos*? How about after you took the קמיצה *kmitzah*,
how would you then take that קמיצה *kmitzah* and put it into
the next כלי *kli* to sanctify it? So אמר ליה נתנה לכלי
זה *amar lei nosno likli zeh*, like you could put it into
this type of vessel. So of course he says, וכי מקדשין בכלי
שעל גבי קרקע *vechi mekadshtin bichli sheal gabei karka*? Can you do
it if it's on the ground? So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so
he said, no, no, no, דמבאי ליה כהן Kohen. *demavei lei kohen*,
I meant that a כהן Kohen. *kohen* was holding it. So אמר
ליה אם כן הוצרכת ג' כהנים Kohanim *amar lei im kein hutzrachta
gimmel kohanim*. So then you need three כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim*. Three כהנים
Kohanim *kohanim*. Oh well, no, how do you... so you got one
כהן Kohen *kohen* holding it. One, I think you need to use
your right hand, right? So one כהן Kohen *kohen* holding it, how
many right hands do you have? One כהן Kohen דעביד הקמיצה *kohen
devei hakmitzah* and one כהן *kohen* putting it on. So you need
three כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*. So is that true? אמר ליה ותהא י"ג
כתמיד *amar lei v'tei tlisha-sar k'tamid*. So what? Maybe we know the
תמיד של שחר *tamid shel shachar*, because he... תמיד *tamid* he remembered,
he didn't remember מנחות *menachos*. So we know that the תמיד של
שחר *tamid shel shachar* had 13 כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* that brought the
limbs up the מזבח *mizbeach*. So big deal. So why not have
three כהנים *kohanim*?
איתיבי *Eisivei*, so I'll ask you on this. By the way, what's
also problematic about this is we normally assume that it's the owner
holding the מנחה mincha. *mincha*, right? וקמץ משם ממקום שרגלי הזר עומדות
*vekomatz misham mimakom sheraglei hazar omdos*. Like he comes with his מנחה
*mincha* and the כהן *kohen*, מקמיצה ואילך הגמרא אומרת מצוה בכהן *mikmitzah
ve'eilach hagemara omeres mitzvah bekohen*. Now, in addition to the idea that
we're saying it has to be held, what we're saying it has
to be held by a כהן *kohen*. We're taking the owner out
of the whole process. Like you give it to the כהן *kohen*
and you walk away. So let's see where the גמרא *Gemara* goes
with this. איתיבי *Eisivei*, I'll ask you on this. So now we're
making an assertion that you need a כהן *kohen*. Before we made
the assertion you don't need a כהן *kohen*. זה הכלל כל הקומץ
ונותן בכלי המוליך והמקטיר לכל דבר שדרכו לילך *Ze ha-klal kol hakometz
venosein bikli hamolich vehamaktir lechol davar shedarko leilach* etc. So we have
a coming-up משנה Mishnah *Mishna* that is going to be about what?
We've talked about לא לשמה *lo lishma*, we've talked about פסולין *psulin*.
So of course the next thing we have to talk about is,
Michael, what's the thing we always have to talk about? פיגול *Piggul*.
Right. Okay, so the next משנה *Mishna* is, you know, if you're
taking it and you're thinking שלא לשמה *shelo lishma* etc. etc. That's
the next משנה *Mishna*. But our point is, it says only if
you do the קמיצה *kmitzah* or put it in a כלי *kli*.
It doesn't talk about the person that's holding the כלי *kli*. Okay,
so ואילו מגביה לא קתני *ve'ilu magbia lo katani*. We didn't discuss
the person that's holding the כלי *kli*. So תנא *tanna*? No, that's
not a question. סדר עבודות avodot, נקט *Seder avodas nakat*. The תנא
*Tanna* is not telling you all the כהנים *kohanim* that were involved.
He's talking about which עבודות *avodot* are important for פיגול *piggul*. And
the עבודות *avodot* that are important for פיגול *piggul* are the קמיצה
*kmitzah*, putting it in the כלי *kli*, walking it, etc. Holding it
is not an עבודה avodah. *avoda* that's relevant for פיגול *piggul*. So
therefore it's not in that משנה *Mishna*. That's not a question. ולא
סדר כהנים *Velo seder kohanim*. We're not talking about all the כהנים
*kohanim*. Okay, בעו מיניה מרב ששת *ba'u minei me'Rav Sheshes*. So they
asked Rav Sheshes, מהו לקמוץ מכלי שעל גבי קרקע *Mahoo likmotz mikli
sheal gabei karka*? So we're still not done. That was an exchange,
but now we realize that according to the opinion that you need
to hold it, we're getting the בעלים be'alim *ba'alim* out of the
picture and we're having כהנים *kohanim* and we're having three כהנים *kohanim*
in this process. So בעו מיניה מרב ששת *ba'u minei me'Rav Sheshes*.
So they asked the same question from Rav Sheshes. מהו לקמוץ מכלי
שעל גבי קרקע *Mahoo likmotz mikli sheal gabei karka*? Can you do
קמיצה *kmitzah* if the כלי *kli* is on the ground? אמר ליה
פוק חזי מאי עבדין לגב *amar lei puk chazi mai avdin legav*.
So we didn't...
we don't have an answer.
Right.
We don't have an answer whether you need a... because there's two
positions, right?
Yeah. So we're still stuck.
But someone else.
Right. One says this way, the other said this way, we're still
talking about it. So they asked Rav Sheshes, so Rav Sheshes said,
go look what they do inside. Inside the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*.
Of course they didn't have a בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* anymore. But
let's look at what a משנה *Mishna* tells us they did inside.
You know, but I get it. It's like I think it's fascinating
because, you know, the whole idea of them learning קדשים *Kodshim* and
it wasn't relevant anymore and so on. So if you're describing let's
look what they're doing inside and you look through a משנה *Mishna*
and you remember that of course that who ever got an opportunity
to look inside the היכל *Heichal*, right? So but now through the
משנה *Mishna* we're able to peek into the היכל *Heichal*. So let's
take a look at what they're doing inside. ארבעה כהנים נכנסים *Arba'ah
kohanim nichnasin*, because it's not just the עזרה *azarah*, this is the
היכל *Heichal* where the שלחן *shulchan* was. ארבעה כהנים נכנסים *Arba'ah kohanim
nichnasin*, four כהנים *kohanim* go in. This is to take the bread
on Shabbos off of the table. שנים בידם שני סדרים *Shnayim beyadam
shenei sedarim*, two are holding two columns of bread that they're going
to put on, one column each. ושנים בידם שני בזיכין *Ushnayim beyadam
shenei bezichin*, and two are holding two of the little spoons of
frankincense, right, that they put on the table. Because what you did
is you had these little spoons of frankincense and then you would
burn the incense in the spoon and the כהנים *kohanim* would eat
the bread. They would do that every Shabbos. That would be like
the קומץ *kometz*, the incense in the spoon. And the bread would
be like the remainder of the מנחה *mincha*. Okay? So each one
had either one column of bread or one of the spoons. וארבעה
מקדימין לפניהם *Ve'arba'ah makdimin lifneichem*, and four כהנים *kohanim* preceded them. שנים
ליטול שני סדרים *Shnayim lital shenei sedarim*, two to take off one
column each of the two columns of bread. ושנים ליטול שני בזיכין
*Ushnayim lital shenei bezichin*, and two to take off the two spoons
of incense, one in each.
Twelve total? No.
Well,
each person six loaves. You stack them.
But they were able to use their left hand too there I
imagine.
Oh that's a good question. Yeah we didn't mention the left hand.
I don't know. Yeah that would have made maybe that was one
of the tricks they learned how to do. What? Pizza. I don't
know or maybe they had a special כלי to help them hold
it you know. Maybe they had a כלי with stacked up and
then you'd just have to hold the כלי.
They're like matzah or they're like loaves of bread that we have
now?
No I mean they weren't risen but they were not
flat they were basically rectangular.
Yeah they're like pizzas but
they also were you know were really three-dimensional because they were like
a square or rectangle. So but maybe they had a כלי to
help them. I don't know. Anyway so let's take a look. ואילו
מגביה את השולחן לא קתני. ve'ilu magbi'ah et hashulchan lo katani.
Nobody's holding up the table. Now of course you could say wait
one minute a
table belongs on the ground right? So I think you take it
off a table that you don't need somebody to hold I understand
but a כלי that is normally held and doesn't belong on the
ground maybe it needs to be held. Guess what? The גמרא does
not make that distinction. The גמרא says הלכתית halachically these are all
כלי שרת. And if one כלי שרת you can take it from
off the ground then from any כלי שרת you can take it
and put it from on the ground at least according to this
approach. And the גמרא does not challenge it by the obvious question
that maybe a table should be different right? So let's just see
that and then we'll end.
ואילו מגביה את השולחן לא קתני. ve'ilu magbi'ah et hashulchan lo katani.
Nobody is holding up the table. לאו אמרת התם סדר עבודות נקט.
lav amarta hatam seder avodot nakat. When you asked from that משנה
about פיגול you said we're only discussing like the acts of
עבודה. avodah. So הכא נמי סדר עבודות נקט. hacha nami seder avodot
nakat. We're only discussing the acts of עבודה. avodah We're not describing
everything that's done. Which means in reality the שולחן shulchan would have
been held. Right maybe it would be held. But we're only discussing
who's doing the עבודה avodah and the עבודה is putting it on
and taking it off even though the holding might be necessary. So
the גמרא says no. מי דמי? mi dami? You can't compare it.
התם לא נחית למניינא. hatam lo nachit leminyana. The משנה we said
originally didn't say how many כהנים were involved. So the basic point
was to focus on the
עבודות, מניינא דכהני. minyana dechahanei. הכא נחית למניינא דכהנים. hacha nachit leminyana
dechahanim. Here we're giving the number of כהנים. Four כהנים go in,
four כהנים come out. What do you know four go with the
new stuff, four take out the old stuff. So we're giving a
number of כהנים. So if you actually somebody held the table we
would have mentioned it. אלא שמע מינה קומץ מכלי על גבי קרקע
שמע מינה. ela shema mina kometz mikli al gabei karkah shema mina.
So the גמרא actually feels this is the proof. You see they
קמיצה from a כלי on the ground because you can take it
from a table. So therefore you can even take it from any
כלי on the ground.
So then you only need one כהן.
So you only need one כהן. The כהן you can get the
בעלים be'alim back in the picture. The בעלים be'alim come with their
מנחה. The כהן takes it. He could either have another כהן waiting
with the כלי or he could put it on the כלי on
the ground. So it's a pretty bizarre proof but at least it
gets the בעלים back in the picture. And now just to say
the three things we learned today about כלי שרת is number one
a debate whether כלי שרת required דעת or not to have their
impact on designating and sanctifying.
רבי יוחנן says it does not. Number two is whether
כלי שרת requires an act that if the stuff just fell in
the כלי שרת it doesn't function. It has to be put in
the כלי שרת. And number three that the כלי שרת can actually
be effective even if it's on the floor of the מקדש. Yeah.
What if it's on a table? Would it work?
Another כלי שרת. כלי על גבי כלי. kli al gabei kli. That's
a good question. I mean it would have to be another כלי
שרת. If it was a non-כלי שרת it would definitely be a
חציצה. chatzitzah. If it was another כלי שרת I'd have to get
back to you.